this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software
hi this is Scott Johnson thanks for
listening to and your support of
software engineering radio this episode
on the mainframe is slightly longer in
duration than average but I think a lot
of good information is to be conveyed I
hope you learn a little about the
mainframe as much as I have enjoy
well good day this is software
engineering radio this is Scott Jenson
and with me on the phone today we have
Jeff Frey with IBM to discuss with us
mainframes and systems II good day Jeff
how are you good thanks great why don't
we start today by telling if you can
tell our audience a little bit about
yourself
some of your education and anything else
of interest okay great well my name is
Jeff Frey and I'm currently an IBM
fellow and the CTO of the systems II
platform I've been at IBM for 28 years
now in fact today is my 28th year
anniversary come to think of it
congratulations and all of that time
either in or around systems II I started
in 1983 as a programmer in what was what
was then called the MDS operating system
development and from there went into
more of a design role and my career has
progressed and I've been lucky enough to
have experience on some of the major
transformations that that systems e and
the mainframe has has occurred in the
mainframe space over over that 28 years
I was raised born in Akron Ohio but
raised in Rochester New York went to
school at the Rochester Institute
Technology where I hold a bachelor's
degree in computer science this what
this was my fundamentally my one and
only full-time career position I've been
a career IBM er since I got out of
school fantastic today we're talking
about your your primary interest here
and in your point of career which is the
IBM system z which has gone by you know
several names in history but you know
most people know System z or today's
system Z as the mainframe that was not
always the case mainframe has is a term
that is used to describe probably a
class of machines or class of
computational architectures can you give
us a little bit of background and
history on the mainframe
yeah sure that the history of the
mainframe as we know it today is is
actually quite diverse as most people I
think would recognize that the current
mainframe computer or system Z as IBM
knows it today actually was born in 1964
and I say that because at that point in
time
IBM introduced the system/360 which was
quite revolutionary in in terms of what
what had preceded it and the idea was to
build a general-purpose machine that
would host any kind of any imaginable
kind of business application to run
businesses on on one general-purpose
machine that was extensible over over
time and in particular one of the
principal design objectives of that
system and which is still in place today
was one of compatibility we introduced
with IBM system/360 a processor yeah and
and a computer architecture that we made
a commitment to to have remain
compatible in the family throughout its
lifetime and to this day we have
delivered on that commitment so one of
the the key aspects of the mainframe as
we know it and I think one of its
properties is is that it has remained
compatible in terms of its programming
models in terms of its compatibility
over over a number of decades now so
that you know we we made a specific
contract to people that make sure that
their investment in applications that
were hosted on the mainframe and system
Z were protected out through time I
think another aspect of of mainframe is
you know there are many different
characteristics of mainframe and I think
a lot of what a mainframe is has changed
over time but I think central to the
notion of a mainframe is is the notion
of a large system that can host lots of
business work and has large
city for deployment and execution of
business work but also uses that
capacity and that scalability to afford
economies of scale that aren't present
with typically smaller environments or
smaller kinds of configurations
mainframe as we know it today and has
been the case since its inception is an
architecture that fundamentally an
architecture that that provides
large-scale shared resources across the
environment so that you know in terms of
whether it's CPU or memory or i/o the
fundamental premise of the mainframe is
that a lot of capacity it's a single
system it has a single administrative
model it can handle lots of work it is
elastic in terms of having all of the
resources shared so you can run lots of
different types of work on that system
and have all of that work run
effectively in low-cost and efficient
we've had a number of players in the
mainframe field over the years and and I
think probably currently we're probably
recognized as as the principal and maybe
the only mainframe provider now you
might might remember that in our history
other large system mainframe providers
Hitachi and and all in particular that
built large systems eor mainframe
compatible compatible alternatives to
the IBM mainframe in fact gene Amdahl is
is of course well known within IBM as
being one of the designers of the
original IBM mainframe and system/360
and went off and to form the EM doll
company to build compatible mainframes
on under his own name today I think this
notion of a large system shared resource
mainframe kind of computing centralized
computing is probably the space of IBM
in particular but but we still are
producing this mainframe under the same
the same architectural
notions as was was the intent back in
1964 and there have been a lot of
changes in the technology but the
fundamental premise of having a large
centralized and centrally managed
compute facility has stood the test of
time determine frame itself was that
that an IBM coined term or obviously I
correct me if I'm not right but was not
mainframe part of a certain frame of
systems and that just happened to be the
main one in those frames where did that
term originated yeah you know I probably
should know that where where the actual
term mainframe came from I can I can
only guess that you know there there is
a structure in place for physically I to
have this compute capability packaged in
in this large you know construction of
frames that are bolted together that
that hosts these these components but I
really couldn't I really couldn't say
actually people still to this day call
things pcs when they may or may not be
but it was a coin you know a phrase
coined long enough ago that it persists
nonetheless so but there everybody
everybody understands it yeah I think I
think what what the term mainframe
actually connotes is is is that of what
eventually became large server right as
opposed to something that's personal
either a PC a personal computer or
personal device even in the movies we
you know you hear people still referring
to getting access or connecting to the
mainframe which suggests you know that
the critical mass of compute power
within some enterprise somewhere you
know that there's a single one of those
in it and it's you know it houses most
of the power of computing for an
enterprise and most of the data for the
enterprise I think that's what the what
the name connotes even to this day even
though it may not represent the same
physical structure as it as it did once
why a mainframe there obviously we're
taking a look here at the mainframe
system in systems II centralized
computing infrastructure versus more
decentralized
or numerous servers and any given
enterprise either physically or
logically you know co-located or
separately located why deploy a
mainframe today and what is the
fundamental difference between that and
other computing infrastructures in the
market I think there are a number of
distinct characteristics of a mainframe
when you look at it and compare that to
other to other computing configurations
or computing taxonomy one of the one of
the key properties I think of a
mainframe is is going back to this idea
of having a very large compute capacity
that compute capacity whether it be the
processing you know the CPUs and the
processors or the memory or the or the
i/o and the storage that is connected to
the machine to have a lot of a lot of
capacity in terms of well compute power
or lots of memory or lots of storage it
could be attached that is all managed
and as a single system with the kinds of
economies of scale that you get for you
know systems of any kind that scale up
and provide that kind of economy of
scale I mean Steve Mills uses the
example of mass transportation as an
example as being the most effective and
cost-effective way to move people around
getting people on you know a few hundred
people on an airplane or on mass transit
is a cost-effective way of moving that
many people across the country for
example it may not be the most
individual freedom of choice in terms of
how people would want to for example get
across the country but it but it does
offer certain colonies of scale and it
does offer the sharing of resources in a
way that fundamentally provides lower
lower cost and lower cost of ownership
and how to how to get that job done I
think that's a fundamental to the
concept of scale as well I often give a
talk and discussing scalability I give
an example of taking 60 children to
school would you like to do that in a
Corvette one shot at a time at a
significantly faster pace or that's cool
bus with 60 children sitting in the back
despite a fact as being slower it
certainly is more efficient and scales
much better despite the speed so yeah
and I think the other the other aspect
of a shared kind of large centralized
kind of mainframe structure is is in
terms of the ability to share things
right part of the efficiency that you
get from from economy of scale is that
not all of the jobs not all of the
business functions that execute on a
given set of compute devices all use
those devices fully utilize all of the
time and so if you can in fact deploy
lots of work on on a shared set of
resources and you've done the right
engineering job to make sure that you're
fair in the allocation of those
resources to each of the each of the
tasks that are running on the machine
you can actually do more work with less
which makes that the notion of economies
of scale it makes you know more
efficient use of of a more scarce set of
resources which is why even to this day
we were able to run mainframe systems at
very high utilizations close to close to
100% in some cases of having all of the
compute resources in the system utilized
at almost 100% while maintaining the
performance objectives and of all of the
work that's running on the system
without starving any any of the any of
the tasks al-khoei and and making sure
that for example in online transaction
processing environments all of the work
is achieving its response time goals by
even even with a system that's that
highly utilized and I think part of it
is a long history of engineering of
having a shared resource perspective in
the mainframe but also it's it's a
matter of this efficiency and sharing
all right so all of the processors are
shared all of the collection of the
entire memory footprint across machine
is shared all of the i/o adapters and
i/o devices and storage is largely
configured in in mainframe environments
to be completely shared which allows for
this efficiency and to make sure that at
any given point in time you have the
highest utilization of the
I am a any given program or generalist
how does that you know share everything
type of model affect my programming for
mainframe let's I want want to target
system Z as a platform does my
programming model have to change doesn't
need to change or should it change based
upon those resources that are available
to me on System z the question of
mainframe characteristics that apply to
programmers is a very interesting one
in fact back to the discussion or the
you know how we would characterize a
mainframe in some cases I think it
probably used to be more so than it is
today that the mainframe was
characterized by its programming model
so when we started you know long long
ago before we even had the notion of
online transaction processing the way
you did work was with traditional batch
kinds of workloads and so that that's
suggested to programmers a very specific
type of programming model you did batch
processing so there's this notion of
processing through files you know a
record at a time and putting protein you
know applications in loops that ran
through a collection of data and did
batch processing for accounting and
billing etc suggested a very specific
programming model and and by the way
historically there were certain specific
languages that were in place cobol pl/1
Fortran etc that offered different types
of capabilities but different
capabilities but I think in the early
days were used kind of identify the
notion of a mainframe was was was
largely described not only by its
centralized kind of architecture etc but
by by the programming models that
supported so we went on from there to
introduce online transaction processing
and of course then the mainframe became
known more in terms of it being
characterized by some of the key
middleware that runs on the mainframe
for example like the the IMS system or
the CICS system and then later db2 etc
so I think that the programmers view of
any of this stuff has changed
dramatically over the years but I think
even today there's still a very distinct
set of programming models that can be
employed on the mainframe and other
systems for very specific purposes
whether it be batch you know people
people look at batch as as kind of an
old archaic way of doing programming but
if you if you look at the notion of
batch processing it actually is a very
necessary and in fact a very modern way
to process certain business functions
within enterprises online transaction
processing is yet another environment
that carries with it a very specific
programming model and there are tools
that have evolved over the years you
know that has defined a certain type of
program is skilled in understanding how
to build high-volume efficient programs
that do online transaction processing is
very different from programmers who have
been traditionally schooled in in the
area batch and even now as we've moved
on to more component based programming
and and business process integration and
workflow still yet another whole genre
of programmers that architectural II you
know engineer the programs in a
different way and use different tools
there's been an advent of message based
messaging based programming so all of
these particular disciplines and all
these particular techniques for building
different types of applications the
mainframe over its history has has had
to adapt and had to accommodate and in
some cases even lead in the definition
of these new programming techniques
throughout its lifetime to the point
where it is now where I think if people
look at the mainframe with a traditional
perspective and say well that's only a
batch a batch machine or you know the
way to the exclusive way that you do
programming on the mainframe is with
cobol or pl/i they're not seeing of
course the fact that we have the most
modern programming environments the most
modern kinds of middleware database
messaging systems service-oriented
approaches now Java based approaches
scripted based languages all of that
full complement of almost any particular
tool or any particular structured
approach that programmers would use is
in fact available on the mainframe
we've even got linux on the mainframe
which is you know an environment that
complements the traditional systems easy
OS based environments offers a
programming environment that is exactly
the same right as the linux environment
for example in that would be hosted on
any other platform so over time what
kind of identifies the mainframe from a
programming point of view has changed
dramatically I think in the beginning it
was fairly constrained in terms of a
particular type of programming or a
particular language that was used and
that's just not at all the case anymore
well it's actually printing your
conversation there about Linux is
probably a good segue to what I want to
talk about some of the features one of
the biggest ones is virtualization
everywhere or at least that's the way I
look at it is that nearly every resource
is virtualized in some case and not just
recently with a big interest in
virtualization but this has been going
on for decades on the subject of
virtualization this is this is another
very interesting discussion to have in
terms of the mainframes contribution to
the overall industry on virtualization I
would argue that the mainframe and
systems II was really the first platform
to introduce various forms of
virtualization if I'm not mistaken I
think a lot of the virtualization that's
you'll find on System z today and on the
mainframe today originated from the Z
virtual machine or z vm product
offerings and now what we what we have
is various levels of virtualization in
the platform you know over its history
there's been so many significant
advantage virtualization on the platform
and in particular systems ease has taken
an active interest and made significant
investments in making sure that
virtualization is as efficient as
possible at some point in time after we
introduced our prism
work which provides the ability for the
the mainframe the system Z to run
logical partitions across a physical
machine we got to the point at some
point a number of years ago where we
don't even offer the capability to run
the system on what's what some people
might call bare metal anymore you can't
actually you can't actually run a system
Z without it being virtualized we we
pride ourselves on that because I think
that even today we have virtualization
even the base platform that is so
efficient literally runs at near-native
processor speeds and part of the reason
for that is not just because we think we
could have good hypervisors both in the
case of the native prism but also in zbm
a lot of the virtualization and a lot of
the sharing that we do integrate it as a
core tenet of the system z architecture
we have an architectural notion called
SCI which is simulated instruction
execution which basically is a mode of
operation of the machine in which the
hardware takes responsibility for the
virtualization so we have virtualization
of processor and memory and of course we
have pushed down the high degrees of
virtualization and sharing into the
system Z iOS subsystem so that all of
the channels and adapters that get to
network and storage is all virtualized
as well and all of this most of the
value and the efficiency we get out of
our virtualization is in fact because
we've integrated so much of it into the
hardware itself so help me out here in
the stack and I all admit I get pretty
confused too I hear zvm z OS Linux I
think you said also something about
prism where do those sit are they layers
of the gen of the mainframe in terms of
hardware are they software and operating
systems that are layered on top of each
other what is a general deployment look
like when you have all these components
great question the general generally the
the layering of the hardware and
virtualization can be described in the
following at the base level you have
hardware just like any other
Holmwood have you have physical
processors memory i/o adapters network
interface cards with system Z we ship as
part of the Machine firmware in other
words integrated prism hypervisor that
is actually part of the firmware load of
the machine so when you physically turn
this machine on and it goes through a
set of initialization and power on reset
there's an initial microcode load phase
that starts to initialize all of the
physical capabilities of the machine one
of the things that happens is that the
prism hypervisor gets loaded and booted
and brought up on the machine and
there's no choice in the matter so we
don't consider that customer deployed
operating system or software of any kind
its system firmware and there's no
choice in the matter and when this when
the system is physically turned on
initialized that hypervisor comes up and
it's always there then what that
provides is the ability for a system
administrator to define and activate
what we refer to as logical partitions
and logical partitions are fundamentally
virtual machines that can be hosted on
the machine and the notion of this
logical partition or this virtual
machine is a virtual machine that's
hosted on the prism hypervisor within
each of those virtual machines then you
can deploy customers are free to deploy
various layers of software in each of
those virtual machines traditionally one
of the first things that gets laid down
in one of these L cars or virtual
machines is an operating system and
within system Z we have a number of
operating systems that have run on
system Z and of course they still do
right given that commitment to
investment protection by the customer
and there are new operating system
personalities that are being able to run
on the system all the time you have the
traditional z/os operating system which
is really the latest name for the long
history of mb/s multiple virtual storage
was the name of the operating system and
we had various names of this which was
mb/s OS 390 ventrally now system Z z/os
but also different other operating
system personalities that can be
deployed in clue
BSE and TPF and of course most recently
Linux on the platform in addition to
that then as an option
customers can deploy special systems the
operating system called zbm which
actually runs in one of those l par
virtual machines as a customer deployed
operating system where that operating
system is actually a second level level
hypervisor the structure here is that
you have prism and that supports a
certain number of logical partition or
virtual machines that we call level one
virtual machines in a selected set of
those l pars you can deploy the CBM
operating system which acts as a second
level hypervisor that supports its own
guest machine and so those are second
level guest where you have customer
deployed operating systems that are
actually running on the CBM hypervisor
that is actually running in one or more
of the old cars what's what's
interesting about this this is one of
the only systems it might be the only
system that actually has the hardware
support for virtualization that supports
this multiple nested hypervisor
virtualization so when I referred before
to the architected capability in system
Z of SCI the simulated instruction
execution the machine actually supports
nested levels of SCI so that not only
the base level prism hypervisor very
efficient and runs at near-native native
bare-metal speeds it's also true that a
second level hypervisor in this case our
zbm hypervisor is also very efficient
because it takes advantage of this
nested level of hardware virtualization
that we have in the box I think this is
a real differentiator for System z most
people might believe that the
hypervisors themselves are responsible
for most of the efficiencies that we
have in system Z and while it's true
that we're very proud of our
implementations of our hypervisors where
we really get the most efficiency out of
out of the system is because we've
integrated virtualization into the
hardware I have to believe that the
virtualization the hardware is not the
only difference in hardware between
you know you stand a Wintel or UNIX
systems you know what hard work
differences or what a core difference
between mainframe hardware and more
commodity hardware the difference
between what I think of as as as
mainframe hardware and let's just call
it non mainframe hardware I think there
are a few dimensions we could talk about
where there's important differences the
one the one important engineering
principle of System z in the mainframe
goes back to a discussion I think we had
a little earlier which is the capacity
the overall capacity of the compute
capacity memory capacity the i/o
adapters the network adapters etc are
all shared across the entire environment
and so while the ability to efficiently
share for example IO adapters
competitive offerings is just now coming
of age especially with virtualization
you'll hear people refer to for example
single route I over chelation and these
adapters you know System z has had that
level of efficiency and sharing even
even its adapter level and subsystem
level for for quite some time I think
that that another major differentiation
for the mainframe in system Z in terms
of its hardware is in a couple areas one
is in in the area of resilience if you
look at the engineering and and I really
I really have to credit the hardware
engineering folks a long history of
providing very resilient hardware and by
that I mean just the inherent checks
inside and the recovery that is actually
burned into the systems the hardware
component rhe I think is still far
beyond what you can find with with
competitive off for example we we took
you know even the most basic stuff that
like double bit error detection and
correction in the memory subsystems or
the ability for the processors
themselves to detect certain types of
error conditions and recover and when
they can't to be able to use sparing and
ripped and recovery capabilities
inherent and
hardware to make sure that you don't
have enough disruption to the work this
is especially true in the i/o subsystem
the system zio architects rightfully so
pride themselves on the fact you know we
have a more complete end-to-end error
checking and integrity checks across the
entire path from data that that is in
the processor and goes through memory
through the channel through the through
the i/o networking fabric all the way
out quite frankly to the storage device
as you might know we have a very
specific storage architecture storage
command architecture IO command
architecture that has a long history of
not only just providing the basics of
moving data back and forth across these
links to externally attached storage but
have has been architected in such a way
that we have the ability to have end end
integrity and error checking and
correction across the entire path it's
my belief that if people really
understood the cases where on
alternative platforms there's an
opportunity for undetected errors that
might result in indebted data integrity
issues they would really they would
really understand the value of System z
especially in its i/o architecture
because a heck of a job at preventing
those kinds of kinds of undetected
errors and problems within the hardware
the other characteristic I think that is
inherent in some of the systems the
architecture we probably get a lot of
credit for those is in the area of
security and integrity again we've got a
long history in system Z of for example
of having very strong and very elaborate
protection mechanisms that are in the
architecture and and are exploited by
the operating systems and software that
runs on the plot to ensure that
unauthorized access even to various
types of memory in the BA are prevented
and that only authorized use of memory
or certain privileged capabilities or
facilities in the machine you have to
have the right level of authorization is
that all controlled by sign
no no that's that's just in some ways
just inherent in the architecture itself
for example we we have a memory memory
system where you can assign storage keys
of various kinds to two individual
frames of real memory those storage keys
have to be have to agree with a set of
authorization and a set of storage keys
are attached to programs that have
access to that memory and if you don't
have you're not running with a
particular storage key that allows you
to have access to that real frame of
memory you get an exception then and the
memory is protected we would also I
think probably the first system to
incorporate write protected memory or a
read-only memory so that you know there
are certain Cape there are certain key
areas of the system that are never meant
to be modified and we have the controls
in the memory subsystem to to configure
those areas of the system in such a way
that no matter what authorization you
have you can't write over the memory so
there you know there are other examples
of inherent in the system systems the
architecture that prevent either
malicious or even accidental access to
to resources that are not meant to be
shared
for example across the various processes
within z/os we refer to those as address
spaces it's it's fundamentally
impossible unless you're authorized to
do so to have one process or one address
space maliciously
or inadvertently access memory for
example that is is owned by another
address space in the system you know
right down to even the specific
protocols that are used in program
calling sequences for example an
application that is unauthorized calls
an authorized system service and there's
inevitably an exchange of data and
parameters that are used in the call
there are specific protocols and
hardware assisted checking that ensures
that that an unauthorized application
can't cause an authorized application
that is being called in kernel mode to
do damage on his behalf and and so we've
taken these things very seriously over
over the number of decades that
the evolution of systems II and they're
still in place today many of these
mechanisms are just not practiced and
just not just not introduced in
alternative system in terms of the
integrity and isolation between virtual
machines on the platform we also take
that very seriously and make sure that
there's no way either intended or
unintended for example to have one
virtual machine or one logical partition
exchange data or exchange or share
resources unintended with another
logical partition this is very important
to certain security and integrity
compliance standards where we do very
well in system Z because we have the
actual architectural technology in place
to prevent unauthorized communication
between two LRS or two virtual machines
on the same physical box and it goes
beyond just you know it these guys that
look at this stuff they're really it's
really incredible because that there's
this notion of preventing covert
channels where we go so far to prevent
any kind of Morse code that could occur
between one one virtual machine in one
partition with another even the effects
of resource usage for example of one
partition are not visible to another it
might form the basis of covert Channel
and it could it could provide the basis
for one set of software in one partition
sending Morse code to a to another
partition through its normal use of
system resources so the security and
integrity guys in system Z go far beyond
you know what I see in alternative
platforms and that's part of the value
proposition of the platform just move on
to databases
most people would say that any system
regardless of size is only as valuable
as the data in which it manages
databases on system Z of course I would
expect db2 there are some others they've
been around you know historically and in
possibly some other vendors that are on
there can you talk to me a little bit
about the databases db2 is that part of
the platform or is that something
separate
and some other any other type of
database activities and other types of
systems that are available in systems II
sure the in terms of databases your your
right to recognize that database data
serving data management is is a key
value proposition of systems a in fact I
think it's probably a core value
proposition part of that is is because
some of the other attributes of systems
a and the z/os operating system in
particular providing very high
performance system services for
transactional integrity security and
isolation as we've kind of talked about
before but but beyond above and beyond
that we have a number of different
database capabilities that can be hosted
on the platform I would say that in each
case db2 being one example these these
really are you can think of these as
separately deployed middleware that is
hosted on z/os images on the on the Z
platform but not really physically so
much integrated into the platform but
hosted in the platform now having said
that each of the databases that are
supported on the platform and especially
within z/os so let's talk specifically
about z/os hosted databases every one of
the databases whether it be db2 or the
IMS database that's that's accessed
through two DL one language or V Sam
which is you know people would
characterize V Sam in some ways as a
database rather than than simply a
filesystem because it has so much
capability and is used as the as one of
the underlying persistence mechanisms
for the CICS online transaction protocol
program transaction monitor but in each
of those cases these databases are
engineered to take explicit advantage of
the platform and especially to take
explicit advantage and exploit the
capabilities of the z/os operating
system with
each of these databases of course they
are engineered in such a way to make use
of the shared shared everything
architecture within within Z they have
been engineered to run very effectively
in a in a scale-up symmetric
multiprocessing environment where
there's lots of thread parallelism going
on across the platform of course each of
them make very effective efficient use
of large memories in in storage in
memory databases caching buffer pools
etc and of course each of them take take
advantage of the security integrity and
availability characteristics of the z z
OS environment as well as being
engineered in that same kind of
philosophical basis to to provide their
own system Z level resiliency and
recovery I think that the most
interesting integration that's occurred
over the last recent past in Z with each
of these databases is that each one of
them have been have been engineered to
take explicit advantage of parallel
sysplex and we haven't talked about
parallel sysplex yet but some time ago
we we introduced extensions to system Z
and the z/os operating system
environment that would allow multiple
instances of z/os and of course it's
databases and its transaction systems to
be clustered to provide a single a
single system image and to be able to
cluster these things together for even
greater scale and of course for to
provide additional availability across a
cluster kind of configuration again I
definitely want to talk about this place
so you were talking about scale-up and I
think we have you know scale up and out
with sysplex going back to the databases
is the VM which is as you know Leeson in
the activities in which I've worked with
you know SM and vcn files record level
files if you will is that specific to
z/os yes
fundamentally V Sam is is a z/os
provided file system and you said IMS is
built on top of that is db2 or does db2
actually use V Sam as its
backing store yeah there's there's
different kinds of different
capabilities that are that are provided
by the Sam
you mentioned V Sam is is a record
oriented access method and file system
that is one of its personalities so if
you're using if an application is
directly using V Sam as it would in
batch application environments for
example many of the use cases within the
CICS transaction monitor provides access
to record oriented B Sam data in a
transactional context that's one use of
D Sam however having said that there are
actually block level and other granule
areas of access to V Sam hosted data as
a file system that are used underneath
db2 for example so while db2 doesn't
necessarily use the record oriented
access to V Sam data it uses a different
flavor of V Sam through a component
called media manager to get efficient
block access to file system data where V
Sam happens to be the underlying file
management system for db2 and the same
thing to some degree true for IMS so
there are various levels of what's
actually presented to the end-user the
application in the db2 case of course
it's relational it's a relational model
presented and published through for
relational SQL for example and it's db2
that actually makes use of the
underlying some of the underlying
capabilities of V sale so V Sam is very
important part of the data serving and
data management system and z/os and it
represents what I would refer to as the
traditional file system now having said
that there are also UNIX based
hierarchical file systems that are also
available within z/os and are used you
know by applications that are built to
use that kind of hierarchical UNIX style
file system but in the case of db2 and
IMS each of these databases also present
their own model and that has
historically been the case and each of
each of these databases have been
extended over the years everybody is
familiar with relational in db2 and as
db2
progressed not only has it focused on
scale and performance resiliency and
sysplex enablement and sharing but also
in terms of feature function with and
you know extensions to programming model
into SQL and handling different data
types large binary objects for example
in XML data within db2 so it's not all
just record oriented in the traditional
sequel and of course with IMS we
continue to have many applications in
the world that are dependent on the IMS
hierarchical model for data that that
has that has served a number of
applications very well and and continues
to let's jump a little bit ahead here
and go right back to what we almost went
to in terms of sysplex so this kind of
gets into system Z scaling and system
architecture scaling and I don't know
much about suspects so I'll walk us
through everything concerning that
system Z as traditionally known or as we
discuss a little bit earlier being a
centralized system a scale up system all
of a sudden sysplex comes along and
allows the mainframe to scale out in
what is sysplex how does it how does it
solve the scale out while still
maintaining the scale up features great
questions on on suspects in order to
talk about sysplex for system z i think
one of the things we probably should do
is go back and and revisit why we did
sysplex in the first place the advent of
sysplex
came somewhat coincident with change we
we absolutely needed to make in the
actual hardware technology that we're
building with the system's prior to
sysplex we we were building by you know
systems will very large images very
large machines on bipolar technology it
was evident to all of us here in in
mainframe world that that we needed to
get on to the what at the time was and I
don't even remember what level it was
but we needed to get on to CMOS and NC
cross CMOS microprocessor design as a
way to move forward
not only in terms of you know the
efficiencies and the scale and to ride
that technology curve but to get on to
get on the right cost curve cost cost
and price performance curve of of moving
on to CMOS and off of the older bipolar
technology at the time we decided to do
this it was a huge gamble and and you
know people historians will look back at
this moment in systems in history as
kind of a make-it-or-break-it kind of
point in point in its history because at
the time I think we were producing
bipolar technology that bipolar
technology we were I think at processors
that were capable of somewhat over 50
million instructions per second at the
time which even by today's standards is
is of course not not not very not very
fast at all but at the time 50 or 60
myths worth of single-threaded
performance in a processor was was quite
good and when we moved to CMOS capable
processors I think we went from a 50 or
60 myth uniprocessor to CMOS which was
only able to give us about 10 or 12 nips
so this was a huge deal and the question
was how were we ever going to how were
we ever going to get on to CMOS and
still provide the aggregate capacity
that our customers needed especially to
to make sure that we could handle the
scale and capacity of the transaction
processing environments that our
customers depended on and so the answer
was to cluster these things together and
so what we did was we out of necessity
introduced a clustered system approach
with that we called sysplex which which
not only introduced very key hardware
clustering technologies and hardware but
was a significant reengineering of the
z/os operating system to be sysplex in a
and and of course it didn't stop there
all of our key
the middleware are CICS IMS db2 MQ
products and then and then in addition
WebSphere and as we as we added more
software under the system the notion of
having sysplex based system design was
core and Antigua - all of our software
stack and all of the z/os environments
so we did it
fundamentally initially for both scale
and availability out of necessity
because we were going from very what we
considered a very a very fast processor
to - CMOS engines that weren't that
weren't weren't all that fast over time
of course you know the CMOS curve has
has allowed us to get back and far
exceed what we could have ever done with
with bipolar and so the initial emphasis
for sysplex which was scale in the
horizontal dimension to have scale out
and availability and no single points of
failure was was kind of in the initial
design point and then over time CMOS
grew up so that we could produce you
know scale up and get back on a very
very large capacity single system images
as well as well as dramatically
increasing the number of processors in
the configuration with our Z 196 that
we've we just announced and are now
shipping
there are 8080 cores of system Z
processor capacity that is available to
customer applications so we we've
continued to do both scale up and scale
out with sysplex over time but initially
it was out of necessity design points of
parallel sysplex was its its its ability
to be clustered around data sharing
technology and and people actually
thought that we were absolutely nuts at
the time when we we put forward a design
that said while everybody in the
industry was looking at clustering
technologies of one kind or another even
even though they were in their infancy
the general the general accepted belief
was that the
only way to scale up a system
horizontally or scale alpha system as I
should say was to partition the data so
that each of the nodes in a clustered
configuration had exclusive non shared
fundamentally non shared access to to
the data that that individual node owned
and so systems were being built where
the common wisdom was that if I had
multiple nodes in a cluster that if one
node needed data that was that was being
managed or attached to another node in
the cluster conventional wisdom said
that the node had to send the owning
node a message to have the data dragged
from storage for example through the
owning node and then across to the node
that needed it and systems the parallel
sysplex put for a completely different
notion it was shared everything
architecture rather than a partitioned
or shared nothing architecture and the
brilliance of parallel sysplex was in
this device we we we invented called the
coupling facility the coupling facility
was an appliance that was connected with
very high-speed proprietary high-speed
interconnects to each of the nodes each
of the system Z processors in a in a
cluster the coupling facility was
responsible for a couple key things one
is that it provided a multi-system
locking mechanism high performance
locking mechanism that would allow each
of the pieces of middleware on each of
the systems in the cluster to obtain
multi-system rocks or concurrency and
serialization control over shared data
very efficiently in fact at CPU
synchronous speed so you could go out
and register your interest in a
particular multi system lock for
concurrency control at CPU synchronous
speeds just as if that lock was local to
your own memory that in addition to the
coupling facility providing very high
performance caching capabilities for the
data and provided the mechanisms to
allow each of the databases on each of
the nodes to take advantage of high
performance
caching and and cache invalidation
across multiple systems it the coupling
facility then allowed for example each
of the db2 instances across each of
those nodes in the system to actually
cache read and write transactional data
locally in the node of the processor and
still allow that data to be completely
shared across the entire configuration
and like I said nobody nobody thought it
was possible it avoided and solved a lot
of problems that even still exist with
partitioned systems and shared nothing
architecture and it was a real
breakthrough I consider parallel sysplex
the data sharing that the engineering
changes to z/os the movement to CMOS
processors one of those moments in
systems the history where was critical
to re-engineer the platform and I think
we're the system Z is a remains a vital
and strategic computing platform today
largely because of the innovation of
parallel sysplex a lot of folks are into
data sharding today doing what you said
you know some of it being shared nothing
but you know let's let's separate it out
email lists from other databases put the
proof back on two separate systems in
terms of that type of data sharding
model what do what does system Z
programmers to think about that when
they have sysplex available the way the
data sharing capability is presented to
application programmers on system Z is
largely abstracted away through this
through the sharing that the individual
database components provide an
interesting kind of capability of
parallel sysplex and its data sharing
capabilities is that largely speaking
the application that is running
potentially even multiple instances of
that application running across the
nodes of a parallel sysplex or of a
cluster all go after data in a way
presents the illusion to the application
that there's no sharing at all and all
of the mechanisms to make sure that you
have data sharing integrity and cache
coherency across the members of that
cluster is
all of that knowledge and all of that
engineering is in the file system and
database layers the reason this is
different than the way people think
about data sharing in alternative
systems and this is less true maybe
today than it was when we introduced it
is that people often confuse shared
access to storage with data sharing our
view is that those are two distinct
ideas it's been true for quite some time
that multiple nodes multiple systems can
have networks shared access to storage
but it's quite a different thing to have
cooperating database instances across
those nodes I'll provide readwrite
access with local performance allowing
each of those instances to cache and
buffer database data in each of their
local memories with assurance of
absolute concurrency control and multi
system cache coherency across the
environment and that's the magic of the
parallel sysplex and data sharing
architecture not so much to have you
know systems that have physical shared
access to storage but the databases
themselves are operating in a completely
shared everything cooperating manner
without the constraints that that are
imposed by message based systems we
would think that the smallest suspects
cluster might be two nodes what's the
largest sysplex that you know about how
many knows that's a great question I I
probably used to know how what the
largest deployed suspects was I can tell
you that the architectural limit for the
members of Asus Plex is 32 and so of
course that kind of scale is is massive
when you when you think about you know
how big a given single system Z is with
its capacity you know with the 196 we
just put out a system that has up to 80
80 cores of system Z capacity and a
single engine so a couple of 32 of those
together is it's like 25
cores quite somewhere right around those
are systems II course so III think that
I'm guessing but I think probably the
the largest production suspects may be
maybe twenty or more nodes in a full
production sysplex that is taking
advantage of full data sharing and by
the way the smallest sysplex
configuration is in fact a single system
you can add certainly single system sis
plexes and by that what I mean what is
that given that our our system is so
virtualized you can have multiple z/os
images or ell cars on a single machine
and have a sysplex that consists
physically of only one Z Z box is there
any benefit to doing that you know for
future planning or something or why
would you put a sysplex on a single
machine well I I think that there are
some advantages in terms of availability
and resilience whether or not it's
physically hosted on a single machine or
not the advantage of having multiple
images or multiple instances of a z/os
workload for availability and scale even
I mean even on a single box you know
sometimes it's not just the physical
hardware that prevents or that suggests
constraints in the ability to scale it's
actually the software right so if you
have software that either in your
operating system or your middleware or
even even specific to the application
that's being deployed that can that can
only scale to so much capacity or so
many engines or so much memory then even
on a single box especially with the size
boxes if we're providing now you can get
the benefit of additional scale out by
having multiple instances or multiple
multiple parts form of sysplex and still
do data sharing right through a
cooperating set of db2 s for example
even if you you can fit all of that
capacity on a single physical box system
or so sysplex is system complex correct
yes yes my short miserable ex was yeah
system come
phlex at the time I think that's what
what where the name came from thinking
and going from assist plaques or to a
single to a single instance or
virtualized instances however many
looking at workload management evil a
whole bunch of workloads
the capacity of mainframe and systems is
to handle these workloads in in almost a
seamless fashion heavy workloads high
utilization sysplex are no we have
there's a lot to manage there what does
System z handle or what facilities does
it provide what programming features if
any does it provide to handle that type
of workload your one of the
distinguishing distinguished
capabilities of z/os in my opinion is
this componentry that we refer to as the
workload manager system z has had and
you know all the way back years ago to
to when we referred to COS as m vs the
design point for system z & c OS based
operating system had always been that
you could host and deploy different
types of work in a z/os image on the
platform and have each of the different
types of workloads get fair and balanced
access to the resources of the system so
that all of the work could coexist in a
given in a given image when you think
about it it's that's really kind of a
textbook definition of an operating
system is to make sure that that there's
fair and balanced allocation of
resources across various pieces of work
that are running in the system all
sharing all sharing those those same
resources that the benefit and I think
the
it differentiates and what distinguishes
systems II traditionally has been not
only can a given z/os image handle
multiple workloads that are that are
deployed on the system at any given
point in time and this goes back to you
know the economy scale bought and the
ability to make sure that you know we
can share resources and and allocate the
use of processor memory i/o etc to work
and interleave you know access to that
shared resources so that we overall get
utilizations up and get very efficient
use of those resources so the ability to
do lots of work or multiple handle
multiple workloads has has always been
kind of a tenant of policy and z/os but
beyond that we take a special pride in
not only being able to handle mental
pieces of work on the system but but
also handle workloads that are very
different in terms of their behavior and
the performance requirements for their
attributes and how they use system
resources so for example if you consider
the behavior and how resources are
consumed by an application that's
running in a batch environment that
tends to have a different pattern or a
different characteristic in terms of how
resources are used and the objective you
know determining whether that batch
application is performing well or not is
much different for example then how you
would judge whether or not a set of
online transaction processing is is
performing on the system system c has
has always been engineered in such a way
that you can take these these two
examples which are you know I would
argue are dramatically different in
terms of their behaviors and and their
patterns for consuming resources on the
system and to and to be able to run all
of this very diverse and despair at work
load with very different quality of
service requirements
at the same time in the same COSM and
that's where a work order comes in we we
have had for quite some time the
underlying mechanisms to allow the
system to be tuned and to support
different classes of work at different
business importance levels and so that
we could effectively manage the
resources across the system for the
different workloads but a number of
years ago we took a giant step forward
and introduced the ability for a
goal-oriented approach to work load
management in the system where in the
past we required a lot of intelligence
and a lot of placed a lot of burden on
the systems programmers to know what the
particular characteristics of each of
the workloads were and then to to
provide the low-level knobs and dials to
tune the system and to set for example
resource allocation constraints or
dispatching priority constraints etc
with these low-level kind of manually
driven knobs and dials we then
introduced workload management which was
a higher level abstraction that allowed
the customers to identify their
workloads and assign goal-oriented
performance goals to those workloads so
that the underlying system could do the
monitoring of system resources and we
are we introduced the heuristics in the
platform to know where the constraints
are where the delays were and then how
to adjust the system resources
dynamically in accordance with the
service level means that they were
associated with that work and how did
that compete or how does that compete
with the classic art of batch
programming so batch programming though
it obviously has its very distinct and
real benefits a lot of was the ability
to schedule certain amounts of work by
the programmers or by the system
administrators in ways that would
balance that workload so workload
management comes around does that
diminish the importance of match or just
change it no I think I think it's that
the relationship between
a more goal oriented approach to
performance management actually applies
equally well to all of the the different
programming environments on the system
including batch so for example to take
you to take your example where in the
past to get a balanced allocation of
resources across the system what
typically happened was the system's
programmers identified different
different jobs scheduling queues and
different classes of initiators of batch
initiators in the system and associated
with those those batch initiators or
those batch execution mechanisms fairly
static allocation of their relative
priority which job classes were going to
get more processor and more memory than
the others and it was a fairly fairly
static and fairly kind of a priori
understanding that said we're going to
define certain job classes with certain
characteristics and and then you take
the jobs that are being submitted to the
system in terms of the batch jobs and
you better target the particular job
class or job initiator that you've been
assigned in order to make sure that you
you know you basically schedule your
work into into a you know into a job
initiator that has the right properties
or the right class as opposed to a more
goal-oriented and dynamic approach which
is to define the workload that's being
scheduled as having a particular
response time goal for a particular
throughput goal or for example declaring
from a business perspective that this
job needs to run in a certain amount of
time or it needs to complete before a
certain time of day and then having the
system understand what those
requirements are for that job and then
to allocate the resources in accordance
with it achieving its goals dynamically
and it's a much different perspective on
you know how the system takes on more of
the responsibility for understanding the
overall service levels objec
is of a particular piece of work and
then makes the adjustments dynamically
without having no kind of an a priori
static you know definition of the
resources and the reason that's so
important is because it's just
fundamentally impossible in many cases
to to predict what the load on the
system is going to be or what spikes in
capacity are going to be needed and so
it was all about not only simplifying
things so that the way in which JA the
way in which work ran on the system
could be defined in a way that had
relevance to the business in terms of
the relative relative importance of that
work to be able to describe its goals in
terms of you know performance metrics
that were actually meaningful to the
business and then allow the system to
make trade-offs based on what what
you've told it about the service levels
and the relative importance of the work
a lot of times you know when the system
has enough resources and everything's
fine and the system has been over
provisioned to handle a certain amount
of work typically you know things run
fine right it's when it's when resources
are constrained or when you have spikes
in capacity or when you have certain
failures that diminish your capacity
that hard decisions have to be made by
the system in order to make sure that
the most important work is is has a
better opportunity to achieve its
business goals potentially while
shedding more discretionary or less
important work and mating making those
intelligent trade-offs that's what
that's what the system Z approach to
workload management is all about goal
oriented service level resource
management intelligent resource
management in alignment with the
business subject let's let's move on to
some language support programming
languages on system Z what is the
fundamental difference if anything
between programming for system z and
programming for say apple unix flavors
and all windows now granted I know that
Linux runs on system Z so not probably a
whole lot would change there but in more
I don't know if I want to call it
traditional but in you know non Linux
system Z environments
how is the programming model any
different programming models are always
that the most interesting part of the
discussion around mainframe and systems
a limit let me I guess I would
characterize how common or how different
programming is for systems in the
mainframe in the following way
I think largely it has to deal with it
has almost nothing to do these days with
the actual architecture of the machine
it has been the case for quite some time
that the actual specific instruction set
architectures for example of the machine
unless you're writing in assembly
language you know higher level languages
and and higher level middleware has
extracted away the fundamental
differences at that level and and those
things don't typically show through in
the programming I think largely to
answer whether did the question as to
whether or not programming on system Z
is fundamentally different or the same
then say programming in UNIX or Windows
or or even on Apple for example has less
to do with the underlying system
architecture you know what physical
hardware you're running on then it or
even what operating system in some cases
you're running on than it does with what
is the programming interface that you're
using so for example within IBM
we have the WebSphere the WebSphere
product that runs across all of our
platforms and fundamentally the ability
to write applications WebSphere
applications whether it be you know
traditional Java j2ee applications or
portal applications or business process
orchestration fundamentally the
programming model for WebSphere is the
same across any of the platforms that
it's deployed on so fundamentally the
way that you would write an engineer an
application in websphere or UNIX or
Windows would be the same as you would
on on System z and z/os in fact many
times it's exactly that scenario that
occurs when people
actually do their development unit test
initial test of their development on on
a personal workstation or UNIX or
windows-based host in WebSphere and then
go through various quality
certifications and actually end up
deploying that application on a system C
or a z/os environment so it has largely
to do with I think you know the
programming tools or the middleware that
you're hosting the application in for
example in db2 you know one might argue
that you know there's a large percentage
of commonality to whatever extent you
know sequel dialog dialects are the same
across across the platforms
if you're writing applications that are
constrained to the standard and comply
with a standard that's generally
available across any of the relational
systems those applications can be hosted
and typically port to the various
different platforms much easier than
applications that have taken advantage
of some you know middleware specific or
platform specific capability in their
application which makes them less
portable so in this in this context I
think that because system Z has such a
long history we tend to ask this
question in the context of system Z as
if specific to system Z and and I would
argue that any of the programming
environments any of the middleware
that's available that people may use may
have different platform variances that
that cause the applications to be tied
to a specific environment whether it's
an underlying hardware platform or
operating system environment or
middleware or programming tool so in
some cases programming on system Z is
very different than anything else for
example if you're writing CICS
applications they are CICS applications
and to the extent that CICS is a system
Z specific piece of middleware then you
could argue that that is a system Z
specific programming model that doesn't
really exist anywhere else if you're
looking at some of the Java
or web services based programming
environments I would argue the other
extreme which is that these programming
models and tools are ubiquitous and
generally available in a common way
across all platforms including systems
II and in those and in that case the
programming for the different platforms
is fundamentally no different then
describe for me if it's not so much
different there which I tend to agree
with what concerning z/os language
environment is there are there features
available there that are I don't want to
call them fundamentally different but
are there features available within the
language environment which would change
the approach of a programming model yeah
that the z/os language environment does
provide in some ways that the z/os
language environment is is a particular
implementation of a set of libraries
that are available to to all of the
languages on the z/os environment and in
some ways is just a different a
different implementation or a different
factoring of those capabilities for z/os
then then it would be for other
platforms much I would say to the
largest extent of what's provided by the
z/os language environment is in fact
providing the system services and
capabilities that are available in the
in the higher order you know the
programming languages that just happened
to be implemented in in a specific way
in z/os so that the underlying
implementation of some of those
capabilities take advantage of specific
z/os qualities of service or tasking or
threading models or recovery models etc
so the whole point of z/os language
environment it is in fact to provide
that level of standardization and
portability for the languages while at
the same time giving us an opportunity
to have an implementation that takes
explicit advantage of z/os and its
capabilities and to differentiate it
okay then normally I would you know
breeding up I've not worked with it but
reading up on us language environment at
all
what would appear to me as though it has
a lot of the same type of concepts of
the.net CLR but I'm not I'm hearing it's
not necessarily a runtime maybe more a
set of common libraries meant yeah I
think I think largely it is a set of
libraries that are implemented in in a
specific in a specific way so for
example a lot of the a lot of the system
calls that you would find in in a C or
C++ language environment in a z/os
environment are delegated down into this
this is z/os language environment
componentry and implemented there but
but from a programming model standpoint
it implements the standard so for
example if you were to do threading or
or memory allocation in C or C++ you
might find that the malloc for example
call would delegate down into a language
environment capability where where that
think that would be implemented
according and use the z/os system
services for memory management for
example in a way to leverage that
capability in z/os but to provide a
portable and standard semantics to the
to the language so largely I think it's
more of an implementation choice than it
than it is in terms of its showing up as
a difference in the programming model
excellent information in in the case of
Java by the way there's another level of
course of abstraction in the java
language given given that it has its own
runtime and its own virtual machine
capabilities where the le environment is
completely abstracted away and so in
what you and what the application
programmer is subject to of course is
absolutely standard Java in many of
these cases the le environment isn't
isn't even exposed in any way to the
programming model or to the language in
some of the older languages for example
a cobol or pl/i there may be very
specific exposure to le and its effects
on the language but in terms of the more
recent or modern languages and
especially
Java it's largely completely transparent
and and not exposed at all so we're
running short on time here and I know
that we've actually gone over but I do
want to ask you about the roadmap he
tell us what's up and coming in this
year it's early spring 2011 on the
recording time now what's coming in for
the remainder of 2011 into 2012 for
System z yeah well we have of course in
terms of roadmaps and what's next we
have you could almost take each of the
products that comprise the overall
systems the environment
and talk about each of the roadmaps
somewhat distinctly we we continue to
have new releases of the z/os
operating system environment where you
know a large part of what we do in the
operating system of course is to make
sure that we have best-of-breed support
for the new hardware we're constantly
adding new features or scale and
availability introducing new
technologies that are available in an
environment like z/os for example you
might look at a roadmap for z/os and and
and may find that we're going to take
advantage of flash memory technology for
example in different ways to make more
efficient for example the paging
subsystem in z/os so there's there are
technology issues there's always you
know constraint removal making sure that
we we continue to have best agreed scale
and availability of the platform we
always are pursuing additional recovery
and availability and resiliency in the
platform there's a whole set of roadmap
items for z/os think about as we move
forward and of course each of the
subsystems have their own roadmaps we
just we just delivered on on db2 version
10 that had many features right both
from a relational programming model
perspective but also in terms of
performance and constraint relief and
additional resiliency from the base
platform perspective we just shipped the
the 196 the next the newest generation
of the box as people might be aware
are typically after we deliver on you
know the first first of a new generation
of machine with a large class of machine
we typically follow that up with with a
business class capability of the machine
with every generation we typically are
on this pattern of of introducing new
machine and then follow up with a focus
on on IO and improving and extending the
IO infrastructure of the machine so I
think we could probably look forward to
that in 2011 another major capability we
we announced as part of this new this
current generation of C machine is the
notion of a hybrid system which
incorporates not only the traditional Z
processor but also the ability to
logically extend System z with with
native x86 and power blade architectures
and so we delivered the first part of
that promise late in in last year of
2010 and we have just delivered on more
integration on what we announced a
statement of direction for that product
which included the now the ability to
integrate data power appliances into the
system and and towards the end of 2011 I
think you'll find win support for native
x86 blades and and x86 Linux and Windows
deployments in the Z Enterprise a hybrid
system as well so there's these are they
should not physically part of the system
itself
yeah the the Z Enterprise it probably
could have a whole other discussion on
on the enterprise but what we did with
this this latest generation of system Z
product was allow customers to extend
the traditional Z processor with
infrastructure we refer to as the Z
Enterprise BladeCenter extension and so
it allows Z the core Z 196 processor to
be extended with x86 and power system
blades with a set of men
measurement firmware across that entire
system so that it so that it presents
that hybrid system to the customer in
terms of its operational control as a
logically integrated virtualized hybrid
system that includes Z components X
components and power components so we've
just started to deliver on that roadmap
it's a major it's a major pillar of the
IBM system z strategy now and we've only
just begun on this and and and there's
much more to do and much more to come in
eleven twelve and beyond maybe that
sounds like it's a its own showing unto
itself
it certainly is all right well I think
that we are probably at the end of our
time here thank you very much for being
with me today you betcha it was a
pleasure and thanks a lot thanks for
listening to se radio an educational
program brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine for more information
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to support us you can advertise se
radio by clicking the Digg reddit
delicious or slash buttons on the site
or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
their episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]